<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4004 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4004.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4950 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4950.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5447 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5447.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5777 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5777.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5778 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5778.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6733 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6733.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7155 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7155.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7423 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7423.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7683 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7683.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7944 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7944.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.bertz-dime-rfc4006bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.bertz-dime-rfc4006bis.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-load SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-dime-load-09.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bertz-dime-diamimpr-00" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
 <front>
   <title>Diameter Specification Recommendations</title>

   <author fullname="Lyle Bertz" initials="L." surname="Bertz">
     <organization>Sprint</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>6220 Sprint Parkway</street>
         <city>Overland Park</city>
         <region>KS</region>
         <code>66251</code>
         <country>United States</country>
       </postal>
       <email>lylebe551144@gmail.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2017" />

   <area>Operations and Management Area</area>

   <workgroup>Diameter Maintenance and Extensions</workgroup>

   <keyword>diameter</keyword>
   <keyword>application</keyword>
   <keyword>errors</keyword>
   <abstract>
<t>
This document reports on formatting errors, uses cases, and inconsistencies found in various 
standards specifications related to the Diameter interface requirements. Recommendations are 
made to reduce errors, support common use cases and build specifications in such a way that 
programmatic verification of Diameter specifications can be done with minimal to no errors.
</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>This document identifies common errors and uses of Diameter in order to document 
     requirements and possible extensions to the Diameter Command Code Format (CCF) and 
     other formats, e.g. Grouped Attribute Value Pair (AVP) format defined in <xref target="RFC6733"/>.  It is by no means an
     exhaustive analysis of all Diameter specifications but provides a survey of a few
     dozen RFCs and 3GPP Technical Specifications to determine what improvements can 
     be made in Diameter specifications.</t>
     <t>There are no issues with respect to over the wire communication of Diameter as 
     evidenced by the successful implementation of Diameter applications based upon the 
     specifications surveyed in this document. However, the development and implementation 
     time of Diameter applications can be significantly improved when errors and 
     inconsistencies of the message format as documented in the specifications are minimized 
     or non-existent. An automated tool was developed and used to perform the survey analysis 
     of the technical specifications. The tool would perform automated checking, syntax validation, 
     and language generation and was ran against the various specifications to set a benchmark on 
     the current state and quality of the Diameter specifications. The '.dia' format of a fork of 
     the diafuzzer project (https://github.com/Orange-OpenSource/diafuzzer) was used. It is a simple,
     deterministic format that provides semantic cross checks of Diameter specifications.</t>
     <t>With the goal of automated '.dia' format in mind a survey of various Diameter related RFCs and 
     3GPP Technical Specifications was executed. During the process several issues, errors, omissions 
     and usage patterns were discovered, and they are outlined in section 4 (Specification Survey) of 
     this document.</t>
     <t>Diameter Applications Design Guidelines <xref target="RFC7423"/> does an excellent job of noting 
     common diameter desing use cases but it does not describe how the CCF or related grammers may represent 
     some of these scenarios. To do this the '.dia' format was extended. A few new use cases were also 
     identified that were not covered in <xref target="RFC7423"/>.</t>
   </section>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
       target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
     </section>
<section title="Survey of Existing Specifications" anchor="Survey">

<t>The tool was ran against the following standards specifications for diameter applications:
<list>
<t>RFC 4004 <xref target="RFC4004"/></t>
<t>RFC 4006 bis <xref target="I-D.bertz-dime-rfc4006bis"/></t>
<t>RFC 4950 <xref target="RFC4950"/></t>
<t>RFC 5447 <xref target="RFC5447"/></t>
<t>RFC 5777 <xref target="RFC5777"/></t>
<t>RFC 5778 <xref target="RFC5778"/></t>
<t>Diameter Load (draft) <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-load"/></t>
<t>RFC 6733 <xref target="RFC6733"/></t>
<t>RFC 7155 <xref target="RFC7155"/></t>
<t>RFC 7683 <xref target="RFC7683"/></t>
<t>RFC 7944 <xref target="RFC7944"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.214 <xref target="TGPP.29.214"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.345 <xref target="TGPP.29.345"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.344 <xref target="TGPP.29.344"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.343 <xref target="TGPP.29.343"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.338 <xref target="TGPP.29.338"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.337 <xref target="TGPP.29.337"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.336 <xref target="TGPP.29.336"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.329 <xref target="TGPP.29.329"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 32.299 <xref target="TGPP.32.299"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.154 <xref target="TGPP.29.154"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.215 <xref target="TGPP.29.215"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.368 <xref target="TGPP.29.368"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.128 <xref target="TGPP.29.128"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.173 <xref target="TGPP.29.173"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.217 <xref target="TGPP.29.217"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.273 <xref target="TGPP.29.273"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.272 <xref target="TGPP.29.272"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.061 <xref target="TGPP.29.061"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.212 <xref target="TGPP.29.212"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 32.299 <xref target="TGPP.32.299"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.229 <xref target="TGPP.29.229"/></t>
<t>3GPP TS 29.468 <xref target="TGPP.29.468"/></t>

</list>
</t>
  <section title="Summary of Challenges and Errors" anchor="commonerrors">
    <t>Enumeration issues have their own section below.  General issues include but are not limited to:
     <list>
     <t>Spelling and spacing errors.</t>
     <t>Inconsistent Table formats over time.  Arguably this reflects the changes in Diameter but
     these inconsistencies occur with documents released in close time frames.  There are also too 
     many formats to claim it is a 'change over time' and not just an inconsistency issue.</t>
     <t>Missing AVPs and/or AVP Code values.</t>
     <t>Case Sensitive inconsistencies.</t>
     <t>The wrong name for AVPs in Tables, referenced across specs, etc. that have the same AVP Code.</t>
     <t>Claiming an AVP is defined in a spec when in fact it is referenced.</t>
     <t>Incorrect references.</t>
     <t>Not noting an AVP is referenced at all but including it in a Grouped AVP or Command.</t>
     <t>Some AVPs mentioned in Grouped AVPs and not defined anywhere.  This happened a few times in accounting 
     related 3GPP specifications.</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>Enumerations do not have a specific format in the base specificaton <xref target="RFC6733"/>. Over the wire the 
    labels themselves are not used as the value is transported in integer formats. When received by a Client or Server 
    the value is checked against a list of valid values.   The label only appears in displayed information for errors, 
    logging, etc.  However, many of the specifications used varying case, spaces and formats such as parenthesis around 
    numbers, tables, numbers then labels, labels then numbers, etc.</t>
    <t>An algorithm keying off of the expression 'is of type Enumerated' was used to figure out the text between 
    enumerations.  A function was then used to attempt to parse various label patterns, generate a label that may be acceptable
    to a coding language and capture the value assigned to the label.  This yielded partial success.  In some cases, especially
    billing in 3GPP, hand edits were required to fix duplicate labels and formats that were inconsistent with the rest of the 
    document's enumerations.</t>
    <t>A few cases even referenced their values as coming from other enums or registries associated with the IETF or other standards
    organizations.  These were removed in some cases due to their size while others were copied from the existing enumeration file in 
    the diafuzzer project if it had already been generated.</t>
    <t>Although enumerations are now available in the intermediate '.dia' format, many of the labels will not be valid in specific
    programming languages.  More work is required regarding enumerations to accommodate these situations.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Summary of Indirect Use Cases" anchor="indirectusecases">
    <t>Several Use Cases appeared that where the dia format was extended to capture them.</t>
     <section title="Refinements" anchor="refinements">
     <t>Refinement (Extension) of Commands and Grouped AVPs.  This is a case where the same AVP/Command is referenced, i.e. same code or
     vendor/code combination but the underlying members of the structure are different.  Two variants of this were found:
      <list><t>The base (original definition) of the structure was refined.  In this case, the 'Refines' Statement in the header
       may not include the application.</t>
       <t>A refinement of a refinement.   In this case the specific refinement (AVP + App ID it was specified in) was the 
       part of the refinement clause.</t>
      </list>
     </t>
     <t>Note: this is not inheritance.  In inheritance the children also inherit the attributes (AVPs) of the parent. In many cases
     the new definition removed some of the parents AVPs or further limited the occurrence amount of the AVPs.</t>
     <t>Refinements can only occur if the Command/Grouped AVP is extensible, i.e. it includes *[AVP] in its definition.</t>
     <t>The rationale for this can be shown by example. A value of 2[AVP] would not be considered extensible and its behavior is undefined.  
     Can someone limit the number of AVPs present in a Command/Grouped AVP when that value is less than the total sum of the upper bounds of 
     all member AVPs.  For example, if a  Grouped AVP permits at most 2 occurrences of AVP member "X" and 2 of AVP member "Y", how/why could/would 
     one limit the Grouped AVP to no more than 3 AVPs? </t>
     <t>In the dia format Refinement is captured by adding 'Refines [application id]' at the end of the header/Grouped AVP definition.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="Enumerations" anchor="enumissues">
     <t>Enumeration use cases included definitions that referenced
     <list>
      <t>other Enumerations</t>
      <t>registries found on the web</t>
     </list>
     </t>
     <t>In the second case the Enumeration was typically removed.</t>
     <t>In a few cases Enumerations referenced other enumerations and then, in Notes, limited the values (was a proper subset). The opposite 
     case (a proper superset) never presented itself.</t>
     <t>Later specifications assigned Unsigned32 as a value in what appears to be an attempt to avoid registries or provide some pseudo 
     extensibility.  The exact purpose is actually unclear.</t>
     </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Summary of Ingestion Barriers" anchor="codegenbarriers">
    <t>Errors, inconsistencies and Use Cases that could not be easily fulfilled aside.  Format differences hampered our ability to 
    quickly ingest Diameter strcutures from specifications.  The following is a list of patterns for just AVP header tables:
    </t>
    <t>
    <figure anchor="fig_1" title="Table Patterns">
    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
Pattern 1: Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in an  
 IETF spec.

The header for an RFC is 
                 AVP  Section           |    |     |SHLD|MUST|    |
Attribute Name   Code Defined Data Type |MUST| MAY | NOT|NOT |Encr|
     
Pattern 2:  Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in a 
 3GPP spec

Attribute Name|AVP Code|Section defined|Value Type|Must|May|Should - 
 not| Must not | May Encr. |
  
Pattern 3: Parses the original table format for AVPs defined for 
 freediameter is BUT some rows define a spec boundary 
 such as the row below the header in this example
 
|Attribute Name|Code|Section|Data|MUST|MAY|SHLD NOT|MUST NOT|Encr|
  
Pattern 4: Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in 
 later IETF specs.

The header for an RFC is
  |                | AVP  | Section |            |    |MUST |
  | Attribute Name | Code | Defined | Data Type  |MUST| NOT |

 An AVP can be 2-line
     Accounting-      483  9.8.7   Enumerated | M  |  V  |
       Realtime-Required                      |    |     | 
     
Pattern 5: Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in 
 some IETF specs like RFC 7155.

The header for an RFC is 
  |                | Section |    |MUST |
  | Attribute Name | Defined |MUST| NOT |
  
Pattern 6:  Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in some 
 IETF specs that don't define applications..

The header for an RFC is 
   |                           | AVP  | Section |                |
   | Attribute Name            | Code | Defined |    Data Type   |
   
Pattern 7:     Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in 
 an IETF spec.
    
The header for an RFC is
                 AVP  Section           |    |MUST|
Attribute Name   Code Defined Data Type |MUST| NOT|
    
Pattern 8:     Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in 
 later IETF specs.
    
The header for an RFC is
|                | AVP  | Section |            |    | MAY |MUST |
| Attribute Name | Code | Defined | Data Type  |MUST|     | NOT |
    
An AVP can be 2-line
Accounting-      483  9.8.7   Enumerated | M  |  V  |
Realtime-Required                      |    |     |
        
Pattern 9:  Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in a 
3GPP spec    
Attribute Name|AVP Code|Clause defined|Value Type|Must|May|Should -
 not|Must not|
    
    
Pattern 10:  Parses the original table format for AVPs defined in a 
 3GPP spec
    
Attribute Name|AVP Code|Value Type|Must|May|Should not|Must not|
      
      ]]></artwork>
            <postamble></postamble>
         </figure>
    </t>
    <t>Even with the patterns present some cleanup for "Notes..." was required to get the headers parsable.</t>
    <t>Not all specifications used an import table.  In fact some inter-mixed the tables used to note AVPs defined in the 
    spec and those that were referenced.  Some columns were removed to ensure that they fit within known formats as well. In 
    other words, there are more formats in the specifications than shown here but with some manipulation they can be reduced to 
    this core set.</t>
    <t>For AVP imports a 3-column and 4-column format were common. Further they often had references that needed to be removed (an 
    enhancement is planned to overcome this in the test code.</t>
    <t>Multiple application specific AVP tables that occurred in a single spec and unified.  This was for research convenience but will hamper
    the generation of small dictionaries.</t>
    <t>Command codes have a long name and three letter acronym typically in a table.  However, neither of those were used in the 
    definition. For example, it is quite common to see Re-Authorization-Request and RAR but Re-Auth-Request in the command code definition.</t>
    <t>There is no easy, programmatic way to identify an application and relations to command codes or result codes.</t>
  </section>
</section>
<section title="Specification Survey" anchor="avps">
  <section title="Survey Process" anchor="survey_process">
   <t>The current process for performing validation is to perform the following tasks:</t>
   <t><list>
    <t>Separate AVP and AVP import tables.  The primary goal of this was to study the table formats
    to develop code to process them.</t>
    <t>Save the file in a text format.  This document is then modified to correct the errors.</t>
    <t>'Repair' enumerations as required through the use of a separate enum file that is modified as
    issues are discovered.</t>
    <t>Create a filter format file that captured data that was hard to find in the specifcation related to 
    Diameter Applications.</t>
   </list></t>
   <t>The time spent for each document is the total amount of time from start to finish where the various files were split as
   described above and the software was then ran.  As errors were discovered they were documented and then, as required, repaired.  In
   some cases new software was developed to accommodate new use cases or formats.  That was added to the total processing time for the
   document unless otherwise noted.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Summary of Errors And Use Cases" anchor="err_usecase_summary">
    <section title="RFC 4004" anchor="rfc4004err">
    <t>For RFC 4004 <xref target="RFC4004"/>, processing took approximately 20 minutes. Defect corrections were approximately an hour.</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>The AVP Table is a unique format. Line continuations of the table are not consistent.</t>
      <t>Enumerations are backwards - # Label</t>
      <t>Some issues were noted but not resolved in 4004.  See  https://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/dime/current/msg02053.html</t>
      <t>Note that MIP-MN-FA-SPI, MIP-MN-HA-SPI and MIP-HA-to-MN-SPI are missing in the specification.  They were removed from their respective Grouped AVPs.</t>
      <t>MIP-Nonce is in the AVP definition but MIP-nonce (lowercase 'n' for nonce) in Grouped definitions</t>
      </list>
 </t>
    </section>
    <section title="RFC 4006 bis (draft 03)" anchor="rfc4006biserr">
     <t>For RFC 4006 bis <xref target="I-D.bertz-dime-rfc4006bis"/>, processing took approximately 25 minutes.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>The AVP table contains inconsistent continuation lines.</t>
      <t>No import tables have been provided and had to be constructed.</t>
      <t>Had to change the User-Equipment-Info-Type AVP to the format of 'AVP (AVP Code XXX) is of type Enumerated' to keep the pattern to one type.</t>
      <t>Had to stub in TBD values.</t>
      <t>Misspelling of IPFiltrRule in table.</t>
      <t>Many enums referenced to registry values in the spec.</t>
      <t>Section 8.6 removes dashes for Check Balance Result</t>
      <t>Redirect-Address-Type Enumerations have spacing so appear as duplicates.</t>
      <t>CC-Session-Failover was phrased as 'is type of Enumerated' instead of 'is of type Enumerated' </t>
     </list>
     </t>
   </section>
   <section title="RFC 4950" anchor="rfc4950err">
     <t>For RFC 4950 <xref target="RFC4950"/>, processing took approximately 15 minutes. No major issues were found.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="RFC 5447" anchor="rfc5447err">
     <t>For RFC 5447 <xref target="RFC5447"/>, processing took approximately 10 minutes. No major issues were found.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="RFC 5777 " anchor="rfc5777err">
     <t>For RFC 5777 <xref target="RFC5777"/>, processing took approximately 3 hours.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>A unique AVP table format.</t>
      <t>Had to hand enter ALL Enum formats.</t>
      <t>The approach taken for enum processing is not correct for this document.</t>
      <t>Treatment-Action listed as Grouped in AVP table</t>
      <t>IP-Bit-Mask-Width not present in table</t>
      <t>4.1.7.7 and table are inconsistent with AVP definition used in groups 'IP-Bit-Mask-Width' vs. 'IP-Mask-Bit-Mask-Width'</t>
      <t>Filter-Rule's use of ';' for comment is unconventional in parsing</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="RFC 5778" anchor="rfc7787">
     <t>For RFC 5778 <xref target="RFC5778"/>, processing took 24 minutes.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
     <t>Continuations in AVP tables are inconsistent which required hand editing.  The continuation '-' sometimes appears on the first 
     line or not until the second which will require more complex code to deal with the situation.</t>
     <t>Imports of AVPs were mixed in with the table definitions specification.  This took the most time work out.</t>
     <t>Subtype field of the MN-HA and MN-AAA authentication mobility options are not defined in spec and needed to be stitched in (corrected) later.</t>
     <t>Although noted properly in text, MIP-Session-Key, MIP-Algorithm-Type, MIP-Replay-Mode was not listed as being imported from an RFC in the AVP table.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Draft Diameter Load" anchor="dimeloaderr">
     <t>For Diameter Load <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-load"/>, processing completed by hand in 10 minutes.  IANA allocations have occurred but the document has not left editors queue which means scripts would not work anyway</t>
    </section>
    <section title="RFC 6733" anchor="rfc6733err">
     <t>For RFC 6733 <xref target="RFC6733"/>, processing took approximately 15 minutes.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
     <t>Continuations were inconsistent.</t>
     <t>The spec does not follow its own CCF.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>  
    <section title="RFC 7155" anchor="rfc7155err">
     <t>For RFC 7155 <xref target="RFC7155"/>, processing took several hours. The original RFC was used to fill in many of the gaps in the AVP table code.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
     <t>AVPs only used for compatibility are in the messages but not mentioned in the document, e.g. NAS-Identifier is still present.</t>
  <t>RA-XXX to Re-Auth but Command acronyms, names and custom names are inter-mixed which is a bit confusing and makes it problematic to automate.</t>
  <t>Hand stitched the enum values which often pointed to entire registries</t>
  </list>
  </t>
    </section>
   <section title="RFC 7683" anchor="rfc7683err">
     <t>For RFC 7683 <xref target="RFC7683"/>, processing took approximately 40 minutes.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
     <t>The AVP table has a unique format.</t>
     <t>Continuations were on the second line requiring look ahead logic.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>   
    <section title="RFC 7944" anchor="rfc7944err">
     <t>For RFC 7944 <xref target="RFC7944"/>, processing took approximately 10 minutes. No major issues were found.</t>
    </section> 
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.214" anchor="ts29214err">
     <t>For TS 29.214 <xref target="TGPP.29.214"/>, processing took approximately 45 minutes.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>In the AVP tables a dot is used as a separator instead of a comma.</t>
      <t>In the Specific-Action AVP, the Label 'Void' occurs twice.  A hand modification was made.</t>
      <t>The Service-Info-Status AVP has spaces between the names in the labels.  This was corrected.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.229" anchor="ts29229err">
     <t>For TS 29.229 <xref target="TGPP.29.229"/>, processing this took 2 hours; 20 minutes.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>Many AVPs are listed as being DEFINED in the specification but they are references.</t>
      <t>It does not import RFC 4005, 7155 or 4006 despite using their AVPs.</t>
      <t>Although restored in Dec 2011 in a change request, Wildcarded-IMPU was not added back to the AVP table 
      Table 6.3.1: Diameter Multimedia Application AVPs</t>
      <t>Line-Identifier also does not appear in the Table and this AVP has Vendor Id ETSI (13019)</t>
      <t></t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section> 
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.468 " anchor="ts29468err">
     <t>For TS 29.468 <xref target="TGPP.29.468"/>, processing took approximately 60 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>Another AVP Table format.</t>
      <t>The Commands were abbreviated in a manner not seen elsewhere in the document, e.g. GA-Request is only used in the command definition.</t>
      <t>AVP Definitions table removes dashes of the Grouped AVPs.</t>
      <t>Duplicate AVP names with different codes for MBMS-GW-SSM-IP-Address and MBMS-GW-SSM-Ipv6-Address.</t>
      <t>TMGI-Number in the Grouped AVP but it is defined in the table as TMGINumber.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>  
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.345 " anchor="ts29345err">
     <t>For TS 29.345 <xref target="TGPP.29.345"/>, processing took approximately 70 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>AVP Table inter-mixes '.' and ',' separation in the flags fields. Code was finally written to overcome this.</t>
      <t>In the AVP Table, App-Identifier was typed as 'Group' and not 'Grouped'.</t>
      <t>In the AVP Table, 'Assistance-info' was incorrect case for 'Info'.</t>
      <t>Section 6.3.31, WiFi-P2P-Assistance-Iinfo has an extra 'i' in it</t>
      <t>User-Identity's, ProSe-Response-Code's and ProSe-Query-Code's origin are unclear.  They is not in a reference section but in several groups.</t>
      <t>Discovery-Auth-Request and Match-Report-Info use incorrect case - ProSe-App-ID.</t>
      <t>ProSe-Query-Code and ProSe-Response-Code are noted in Grouped AVPs but do not exist elsewhere in the spec.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.344 " anchor="ts29344err">
     <t>For TS 29.344 <xref target="TGPP.29.344"/>, processing took approximately 50 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>ProSe-Subscriber-Information-Request is the name for ProSe-Initial-Location-Information-Request.</t>
      <t>Authorized-Discovery-Range was not listed as a defined AVP and has no values assigned.  Filled in as 3708 but these sections are not present in 29.230 at all</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section> 
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.343 " anchor="ts29343err">
     <t>For TS 29.343 <xref target="TGPP.29.343"/>, processing took approximately 10 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>No issues.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section> 
        <section title="3GPP TS 29.338 " anchor="ts29338err">
     <t>For TS 29.338 <xref target="TGPP.29.338"/>, processing took approximately 55 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>Table 6.3.2.2/1: Command-Code values for SGd/Gdd has spaces in the command names.</t>
      <t>Send-Routing-info-for-SM-Answer in the command definition is lowercase and can't be linked to the command table.</t>
      <t>Not an issue but an observation.  There is no Load Control draft reference.</t>
      <t>SGSN-Absent-User-Diagnostic SM has a space in it in the AVP table</t>
      <t>SM-Delivery- Failure-Cause has spacing issue in table.</t>
      <t>SMSMI-Correlation-ID has dash issues in its definition..</t>
      <t>SM-Delivery-Not-Intended has values as a list with ending of ',' and period.  Similar issues for SM-RP-MTI</t>
      <t>MME-SM-Delivery-Outcome- There is an extra &gt; at the end of the header definition</t>
      <t>SM-Enumerated-Delivery-Failure-Cause used ',' and '.' for the list.  Also the data type 'Enumerated' was not capitalized
      causing a miss in the system.</t>
      <t>MSISDN import is from 29.329 and not 23.329</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.337 " anchor="ts29337err">
     <t>For TS 29.337 <xref target="TGPP.29.337"/>, processing took approximately 20 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>No issues.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.336 " anchor="ts29336err">
     <t>For TS 29.336 <xref target="TGPP.29.336"/>, processing took approximately 9 hours as it was used for testing.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
        <t>Spacing issues in AVP tables for Maximum Latency, Maximum Response Time</t>
      <t>Scheduled-communication-time definition is lower case.</t>
      <t>Periodic-Time is lowercase in the AVP Table.</t>
      <t>Found a '/' in the Flags portion of the AVP Table.</t>
      <t>eNodeB-ID and Extended-eNodeB-ID in this spec but 'Id' in defining spec .217</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>  
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.329 " anchor="ts29329err">
     <t>For TS 29.329 <xref target="TGPP.29.329"/>, processing took approximately a billion minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
        <t>Spacing issues in AVP User-Data-Request command. </t>
        <t>Does not specify the Supported-Features, Feature-List, Feature-List-ID, Supported-Applications, Server-Name, Public-Identity from another app in the AVP table.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 32.299" anchor="ts32299err">
     <t>For TS 32.399 <xref target="TGPP.32.299"/>, processing took approximately 9 hours</t>
     <t>
     <list>
        <t>Unique Table format.</t>
        <t>Required to remove imported AVPs and create a new table.</t>
        <t>UTF8string case incorrect in AVP table for a number of entries.</t>
        <t>ProSe-Direct-Communication- Transmission-Data-Container and Status- AS-Code have spaces.</t>
        <t>LCS-Client-ID changed to LCS-Client-Id.</t>
        <t>ProSe-Direct-Communication- Transmission-Data-Container</t>
        <t>Related- Change-Condition- Information</t>
        <t>Trunk-Group-ID was Trunk-Group-Id in AVP table.</t>
        <t>Wrote more software to deal with the values flipped in enums (int first then label)</t>
        <t>Enums were a large issue so hand editing had to take place to clean up the values.</t>
        <t>'is of type of Enumerated' and 'is of type enumerated' were present in the document</t>
        <t>AoC-Service-Type had to be repaired by hand as the algorithm picked up the overloaded Change-Condition values</t>
        <t>MBMS-User-Service-Type</t>
        <t>Node-Functionality needs fixing</t>
        <t>Online-Charging-Flag had to be corrected</t>
        <t>Originator had missing elements</t>
        <t>Void numbers get caught in enums</t>
        <t>PoC-Event-Type used semicolons</t>
        <t>ProSe-Direst-Discovery-Mode spelling issue</t>
        <t>ProSe- Role-Of-UE spacing issue</t>
        <t>Participant-Access-Priority  uses colons in enum labels and mixed descriptions</t>
        <t>Changed Type-Number Unsigned32 as the registry is too difficult to code</t>
        <t>Submission-Timestamp not defined</t>
        <t>PoC-User-Role-Ids instead of PoC-User-Role-IDs</t>
        <t>Removed [ Monitored-HPLMN-Identifier ] as it made no sense and was not defined</t>
     <t>[ Prose-Function-PLMN-Identifier ] removed</t>
        <t>[ VASP-Id ] &amp; [ VAS-Id ] removed from MMS-Information</t>
        <t>Service-Generic-Information removed from Service-Information defined in OMA-DDS-Charging_Data [223].</t>
     <t>[ 3GPP-Session-Stop-Indicator ] removed</t>
        <t>IM-Information DCD-Information removed from Service-Information defined in OMA-DDS-Charging_Data [223]</t>
        <t>ePDG-Address vs EPDG-Address</t>
        <t>M2M-Information removed from Service-Information as it was missing</t>
        <t>SM-Device-Trigger-Information's Reference-Number removed since it was missing</t>
        <t>Incoming-Trunk-Group-ID removed</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.154" anchor="ts29154err">
     <t>For TS 29.154 <xref target="TGPP.29.154"/>, processing took approximately 10 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
        <t>Variance of a later Table format.</t>
        <t>Command Codes were abbreviated in such a way that they had to be changed so the software could match them up properly</t>
        <t>Time-window grouped AVP definition corrected to Time-Window</t>       
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.215" anchor="ts29215err">
     <t>For TS 29.215 <xref target="TGPP.29.215"/>, processing took approximately 60 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
        <t>S9a* reference table has a TS reference instead of 3GPP TS.</t>
        <t>UE-Local-IPv6-Prefix type in AVP table is all lower case.</t>
        <t>Note that ' is of type of Enumerated" was corrected to allow the software to catch the Subsession-Operation and DRA-Binding.</t>
        <t>Imports are missing.</t>
        <t>Change Framed-Ipv6-Prefix to Framed-IPv6-Prefix.</t>
        <t>Logical-Access-ID to Logical-Access-Id</t>
        <t>Physical-Access-ID to Physical-Access-Id</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.368 " anchor="ts29368err">
     <t>For TS 29.368 <xref target="TGPP.29.368"/>, processing took approximately 20 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>TS used in imported AVP tables.</t>
      <t>Command Codes were abbreviated in such a way that they had to be changed so the software could match them up properly.</t> 
      <t>'Feature-Supported-In-Final-Target AVP' in the AVP definitions table.</t>
      <t>External-Id used instead of External-Identifier.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.128 " anchor="ts29128err">
     <t>For TS 29.128 <xref target="TGPP.29.128"/>, processing took approximately 30 minutes</t>
     <t>
     <list>
   <t>Result Codes were not found</t>
   <t>DRMP definitions are not handled.</t>
   <t>Non-IP-Data had type of OctetString</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.173 " anchor="ts29173err">
     <t>For TS 29.173 <xref target="TGPP.29.173"/>, processing took approximately 25 minutes</t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.217 " anchor="ts29217err">
     <t>Processing took approximately 43 minutes.</t>
     <t>The Modify-Uecontext-Request / Answer command definitions did not match anything in the Command Table.</t>
 </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.273 " anchor="ts29273err">
     <t>For TS 29.273 <xref target="TGPP.29.273"/>, processing took 60 minutes.</t>
     <t><list>
      <t>The AN-Trusted enum wasn't picked up by the code.</t>
   <t>Transport-Acess-Type - misspelling resulting in loss in the document.</t>
   <t>Case issue - Subscription-ID vs Subscription-Id</t>
   <t>MIP6-Feature-Vector shows as 64 bit in the document but 32 in RFC 5447.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.272 " anchor="ts29272err">
     <t>For TS 29.272 <xref target="TGPP.29.272"/>, processing took approximately 3 hours. Multiple issues were found but this document
      was used as a reference for development and not considered in processing efficiencies
      calculations.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>Table 7.3.1/1: S6a/S6d, S7a/S7d and S13/S13' specific Diameter AVPs Alert-Reason has type of 'Enumerate'</t>
   <t>ProSe-Subscription-Data Grouped AVP has a type ID of 'xxx'</t>
   <t>Supported-Services AVP has a type of 'zzzz'</t>
   <t>'Subscriber Status' AVP needs a dash</t>
   <t>'Notification- To-UE-User' has a space.</t>
   <t>'IDR- Flags' has a space.</t>
   <t>'Monitoring Event Report' has multiple spaces.</t>
   <t>'eNodeB-ID' and 'Extended-eNodeB-ID' in this spec but 'Id' in defining spec .217</t>
   <t>Claims QoS-Capability as a defined AVP but it is part of RFC 5777</t>
   <t>Trace-Depth is an enum in 32.422 and had to be manually added.</t>
   <t>Job-Type reference vague. From the specification, 'The possible values are those defined in 3GPP TS 32.422 [23] for Job-Type.'</t>
   <t>'Report Interval' has a space.</t>
   <t>Preferred-Data-Mode was listed as a Grouped type but is Unsigned32.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.061 " anchor="ts29061err">
     <t>For TS 29.2061 <xref target="TGPP.29.061"/>, processing took approximately 2 hours.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
     <t>Enums use 'AVP code' vs. 'AVP Code'</t>
     <t>3 AVP tables created for 4 of the apps</t>
     <t>Enums have to be added by hand as they are not tied by application ID</t>
     <t>Messages did not have App IDs in the CCF headers as they are extensions</t>
     <t>MBMS-Session-Repetition-Number has 'M.V' ('.' instead of comma)</t>
     <t>MBMS-User-Data-Mode-Indication Enumeration uses spaces for its label values</t>
     <t>3BPP-PDP-Type - Enum defined as RADIUS; not available to parser in Diameter</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section> 
    <section title="3GPP TS 29.212 " anchor="ts29212err">
     <t>For TS 29.212 <xref target="TGPP.29.212"/>, processing took approximately 7 hours.</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>Logical-Access-ID and Physical-Access-ID have case inconsistencies with other specifications.</t>
   <t>Acronyms in the command code lines but they do not correlate to previously described acronyms in the document.</t>
   <t>Table 5c.6.1.1 is incomplete.</t>
   <t>Periods, '.', were used as separators in AVP tables, e.g.'M.V'.</t>
      <t>Sd and St use TS-Request and TS-Answer but they are don't have application assigned codes.</t>
   <t>'Enumerated' appears in a type definition</t>
   <t>Incorrect reference of 7863 vs 7683</t>
   <t>Manual correction was required in the document.  Somehow PCC-Rule-Status did not got the enums it needed.  
    It appears no spacing created an error.  Hopefully software can be updated to overcome this.</t>
   <t>Pre-emption Vulnerability (in the Section's first line) spacing kills the correct name identification.</t>
   <t>In many Enumerations there is an extra space between 'of type' and 'Enumerated'</t>
   <t>PCC-Rule-Status has a label of 'TEMPORARILY INACTIVE'</t>
   <t>Bearer-Control-Mode 'is of type of Enumerated' issue</t>
   <t>Network-Request-Support Label spaces</t>
   <t>For the Default-Access AVP - 'The values defined in the Default-Access AVP are the same as the ones defined in IP-CAN-Type AVP.'</t>
   <t>Also, mentions '3GPP-EPS IP-CAN' as an option but it is not an option in the referenced type.</t>
   <t>CS-Service-QoS-Request-Operation 'is type of Enumerated, </t>
   <t>CS-Service-Resource-Failure-Cause AVP (AVP code2814) has a spacing issue </t>
   <t>'Logical-Access-ID to 'Logical-Access-Id'</t>
   <t>CS-Service-QoS-Request-Identifier is in table as CS-Service-Qos-Request-Identifier</t>
   <t>Some enumerations with duplicate labels, e.g. Specific-Action</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
<section title="Recommendations for Specification Improvement and Automation" anchor="improvements">
  <section title="Error Reduction" anchor="errorreductions">
    <t>The overall recommendations are as follows:</t>
    <t>
    <list>
     <t>The name of all AVPs, Commands and Grouped AVPs appear consistently throughout the document.</t>
     <t>The letter case MUST be consistent for all names.</t>
     <t>No spaces should appear in the names.</t>
     <t>Use of underscores is discouraged except for line continuations in tables.</t>
    </list>
    </t>
    <section title="Defined AVPs" anchor="avp_errorreductions">
     <t>This section addresses AVPs defined in the specification. 
     The following recommendations are made:</t>
     <t><list>
      <t>Tables MUST include the following columns:
       <list>
        <t>Attribute Name</t>
        <t>AVP Code</t>
        <t>Section Defined</t>
        <t>Data Type</t>
        <t>AVP Flag Rules for MUST and MUST NOT</t>
       </list>
      </t>
      <t>Tables MAY include Notes and other notations in the column headers but
      MUST NOT exceed more than 8 lines of text to describe the header.</t>
      <t>The columns may be separated by space, '|' or both when in text format
    that follows one of the following styles.
    <list>
     <t>All columns except AVP Flags are separated by whitespace and Flag
     column boundaries are pipe delimited.</t>
     <t>Pipe delimited columns with the exception of the first column.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
   <t>AVP Names MUST NOT have spaces or underscores.</t>
   <t>Use '.' or ',' as Flag separators.  Although no space is also acceptable.</t>
   <t>Use of two lines for an AVP is permitted. The following conditions apply. 
    <list>
     <t>An underscore MUST be used at the end of the first line 
     or at the beginning of the second (not both).</t>  
     <t>An underscore is not a part of the AVP name</t>
     <t>All other columns except the Name MUST appear on the same line.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
   <t>All Defined AVP Tables in the specification MUST use the same header format.</t>
   <t>Imported or Re-used AVPs MUST NOT be present in defined AVP tables.</t>
    </list></t>
    <t>
    <figure anchor="fig_2" title="Accepted Table Patterns">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   Example One
   
                   AVP  Section             |    |MUST |
   Attribute Name  Code Defined  Data Type  |MUST| NOT |
   -----------------------------------------|----+-----|
   AVP-Name          85  9.8.2   Unsigned32 | M  |  V  |
   
   Example Two
   
                  | AVP  | Section |            |    |MUST |
   Attribute Name | Code | Defined | Data Type  |MUST| NOT |
   ---------------|------+---------+------------+----+-----|
   AVP-Name       |  85  | 9.8.2   | Unsigned32 | M  |  V  |               
      ]]></artwork>
            <postamble></postamble>
         </figure>
       </t>    
       <t>An open question exists when multiple AVPs tables are present and associated with 
       a specific application within the specification. How the application can be associated
       to the table is an open question.</t>
    </section>  
    <section title="Imported AVPs" anchor="imported_errorreductions">
     <t>Imported or Re-used AVPs MUST be included in the specification.  A table
     MUST be present if AVPs are re-used/imported.</t>
     <t>The table MUST include the AVP and Source document columns.</t>
     <t>The table MAY include a Comment column.</t>
     <t>An M-bit column MAY be present as required.</t>
     <t>The table MUST be pipe delimited when in text format.</t>
    </section>  
    <section title="Grouped AVPs" anchor="gavp_errorreductions">
     <t>When a Grouped AVP is refined a Refine keyword is appended to the end
     of the header.  It MUST include an application identifier of the Grouped AVP 
  it refines if that application was not the original specification or 'version'
  of the Grouped AVP.   When the Grouped AVP refines the original definition of the
  Gropued AVP it SHOULD include the referenced application identifier.</t>
     <t>The refined Grouped AVP MUST be included in the AVP Import table and NOT in the defined AVPs table.</t>
     <t>Open question, should the vendor and application identifiers of the application 
     that created be in the Grouped AVP header?</t>
     <t>When refining a Grouped AVP the following conditions apply:</t>
     <t>
     <list>
      <t>The original AVP MUST be extensible, i.e. it MUST have the '*[AVP]' member.</t>
      <t>Any refinement of an AVP present in the refined Group MUST adhere to the 
      restrictions, if any, that were defined by inherited Groups.  For example,
      if a Grouped AVP refines an attribute 'Foo' to the range X*Y and 'Foo'x is 
      defined in the original AVP with a range of A*B then X &gt;= A and Y &lt;= B.</t>
      <t>AVPs retained without further restriction of the number of occurrences MUST
      be kept in the Refining AVP's definition otherwise they are assumed to be
      dropped from the new AVP definition.  Otherwise, it is impossible to determine
      the Author's intent.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
     <t>Open question, can a Grouped AVP have a range limited [AVP] member, e.g. 
     *5[AVP]?</t>
     <t>Figure <xref target="fig_3"/> shows an example refinement.  In it all but
     the User-Name AVP are dropped in the new definition.</t>
     <t>
     <figure anchor="fig_3" title="Refined AVP from TS 29.128 and TS 29.336">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
From TS 29.336
User-Identifier ::= <AVP-Header: 3102, 10415>
  [User-Name]
  [MSISDN]
  [External-Identifier]
  [LMSI]
  *[AVP]          
            
From TS 29.128
User-Identifier ::= <AVP-Header: 3102, 10415, Refines>
  [User-Name]
  *[AVP]
                ]]></artwork>
            <postamble></postamble>
         </figure>
       </t> 
    </section>  
    <section title="Command Errors" anchor="commanmd_errorreductions">
     <t>The largest issue with Commands is the inconsistent values between the 
     name, three letter acronym defined in the table and the actual name used 
     in the command definition.  Maintaining consistency will resolve this issue.</t>
     <t>Like Grouped AVP refinement, a Refine keyword is appended to the end
     of the header.  It MUST include an application identifier of the Command 
  it refines if that application was not the original specification or 'version'
  of the Command.   When the Command refines the original definition of the
  Command it SHOULD include its application identifier.</t>
  <t>When refining a Command the following conditions apply:</t>
     <t><list>
      <t>The original Command MUST be extensible, i.e. it MUST have the '*[AVP]' member.</t>
      <t>Any refinement of an AVP present in the refined Command MUST adhere to the 
      restrictions, if any, that were defined by inherited Commands.  For example,
      if a Command refines an attribute 'Foo' to the range X*Y and 'Foo' is 
      defined in the original Command with a range of A*B then X &gt;= A and Y &lt;= B.</t>
      <t>Commands retained without further restriction of the number of occurrences MUST
      be kept in the Refining Command's definition otherwise they are assumed to be
      dropped from the new Commands definition.  Otherwise, it is impossible to determine
      the Author's intent.</t>
     </list></t>
    </section> 
    <section title="Enumeration Errors" anchor="enum_errorreductions">
     <t>Enumeration Value Names MUST adhere to alphanumeric and underscore characters.</t>
     <t>Enumeration Value Names MUST not begin with an underscore.</t>
     <t>When being defined the format MUST include the label and the value assigned
     with the label enclosed in parenthesis on a single.  Otherwise, this will confusion when
     the label values end in integers and are close to the numeric value.  For example,
     'speed_10 10' is okay, 'speed_1010' is a error.  This can be avoided by requiring
     the enclosure of the values in parenthesis, e.g. 'speed_10 (10)' and 'speed_10(10)'.
     The last example may not be as readable as desired but it can be understood. 
     </t>
    </section>   
  </section>
  <section title="Formats for automated validation" anchor="codegen">
    <t>This section discusses ways by which further clarity can be defined in a specification
    and automated validation can occur for a diameter application.</t>
    <t>Following the recommendations in the previous section will reduce errors but there are
    still many pieces of information that cannot be programmatically validated.  This includes 
    the following:</t>
  <t><list>
   <t>GAP 1: The application identifier and name of an application.</t>
   <t>GAP 2: The application and vendor identifiers associated with a defined AVP table.</t>
   <t>GAP 3: The application and vendor identifiers associated with Commands.</t>
   <t>GAP 4: Reused and newly defined result codes for an application.</t>
   <t>GAP 5: Easily parsed enumerations that cover all use cases.</t>
  </list></t>
  <t>The following formats show an example of how information could be added to an Appendix to 
  close these gaps.</t>
      <t>
     <figure anchor="fig_4" title="Example Application and Result Code Formats">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
1: AppFoo ::= <Diameter Application: 10415 101010>
2: Command1-Name-Request C1R
3:  Command1-Name-Answer C1A
4:  
5: Result-Codes ::= <Diameter Result-Codes: 101010>
6:  NEW_RESULT (4999)
7:  IMPORTED_RESULT IMPORT (4010)
               ]]></artwork>
          <postamble></postamble>
       </figure>
   </t>  
   <t>GAP 1 is closed in line 1.  GAP 3 is closed in lines 1 through 3 while GAP 4
   is closed by lines 5 through 7.</t>
   <t>GAP 2 can be closed by using a common discernable Table Name format, e.g. AppFoo defined
   AVPs.  In this case the Application Name can be looked up and associated to the defined AVP table.</t>
     <t>Gap 5 can be partially closed by following a pattern similar to Result-Codes but this does not resolve all
     uses cases.</t>
       <t>
     <figure anchor="fig_5" title="Example Enumeration AVP">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
Result-Codes ::= <Diameter Enumeration: 123, 45678>
  Label_1 (0)
  LABEL_Two (2)
               ]]></artwork>
          <postamble></postamble>
       </figure>
   </t>      
   <t>Further work is required to comprehensively cover all Enumeration Use Cases.</t>
  </section>
</section>
<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
</section>
   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   This document is informational and provides some guidance on issues
   related to formatting and possible extensions of the Diameter CCF
   to improve understanding and code generation capabilities.  It has no
   impact to the Security of Diameter or Diameter applications.
</t>
   </section>
 </middle>
 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     &RFC2119;
     &RFC6733;
   </references>
   <references title="Informative References">
     &RFC4004;
     &RFC4950;
     &RFC5447;
     &RFC5777;
     &RFC5778;
     &RFC7155;
     &RFC7423;
     &RFC7683;
     &RFC7944;
     &I-D.bertz-dime-rfc4006bis;
     &I-D.ietf-dime-load;
     
 <reference anchor="TGPP.29.214">
     <front>
      <title>Policy and charging control over Rx reference point</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.214 14.3.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29214.htm"/>
     </reference>

 <reference anchor="TGPP.29.345">
     <front>
      <title>Inter-Proximity-services (Prose) function signalling aspects; Stage 3</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.345 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29345.htm"/>
     </reference>

 <reference anchor="TGPP.29.344">
     <front>
      <title>Proximity-services (ProSe) function to Home Subscriber Server (HSS) aspects; Stage 3</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.344 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29344.htm"/>
     </reference>

 <reference anchor="TGPP.29.343">
     <front>
      <title>Proximity-services (ProSe) function to ProSe application server aspects (PC2); Stage 3</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.343 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29343.htm"/>
     </reference>

 <reference anchor="TGPP.29.338">
     <front>
      <title>Diameter based protocols to support Short Message Service (SMS) capable Mobile Management Entities (MMEs)</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.338 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29338.htm"/>
     </reference>

 <reference anchor="TGPP.29.337">
     <front>
      <title>Diameter-based T4 Interface for communications with packet data networks and applications</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.337 14.0.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29337.htm"/>
     </reference>

 <reference anchor="TGPP.29.336">
     <front>
      <title>Home Subscriber Server (HSS) diameter interfaces for interworking with packet data networks and applications</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="15" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.336 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29336.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.329">
     <front>
      <title>Sh interface based on the Diameter protocol; Protocol details</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.329 14.2.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29329.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.154">
     <front>
      <title>Service capability exposure functionality over Nt reference point</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.154 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29154.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.215">
     <front>
      <title>Policy and Charging Control (PCC) over S9 reference point; Stage 3</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.215 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29215.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.368">
     <front>
      <title>Tsp interface protocol between the MTC Interworking Function (MTC-IWF) and Service Capability Server (SCS)</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.368 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29368.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.128">
     <front>
      <title>Mobility Management Entity (MME) and Serving GPRS Support Node (SGSN) interfaces for interworking with packet data networks and applications</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.128 14.2.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29128.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.173">
     <front>
      <title>Location Services (LCS); Diameter-based SLh interface for Control Plane LCS</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.173 14.0.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29173.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.217">
     <front>
      <title>Policy and Charging Control (PCC); Congestion reporting over Np reference point</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.217 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29217.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.273">
     <front>
      <title>Evolved Packet System (EPS); 3GPP EPS AAA interfaces</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="15" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.273 14.2.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29273.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.272">
     <front>
      <title>Evolved Packet System (EPS); Mobility Management Entity (MME) and Serving GPRS Support Node (SGSN) related interfaces based on Diameter protocol</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="15" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.272 14.3.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29272.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.061">
     <front>
      <title>Policy and Charging Control (PCC); Reference points</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.061 14.3.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29061.htm"/>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.212">
     <front>
      <title>Policy and Charging Control (PCC); Reference points</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.212 14.3.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29212.htm"/>
     </reference>
     
     <reference anchor="TGPP.32.299">
     <front>
      <title>Telecommunication management; Charging management; Diameter charging applications</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="17" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="32.299 14.3.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/32299.htm"/>
     </reference>
     
     <reference anchor="TGPP.29.229">
     <front>
      <title>Cx and Dx interfaces based on the Diameter protocol; Protocol details</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.229 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29229.htm"/>
     </reference>
     
    <reference anchor="TGPP.29.468">
     <front>
      <title>Group Communication System Enablers for LTE (GCSE_LTE); MB2 reference point; Stage 3</title>
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
      <date day="16" month="March" year="2017"/></front> 
      <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.468 14.1.0"/>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/29468.htm"/>
     </reference>
   </references>
 </back>
</rfc>

